Guide to the John Hay Whitney Foundation Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Hay Whitney Foundation records
1946-1994
MS 1952
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
83
(101 boxes)
The records document the organization and activities of the John Hay Whitney Foundation, a nonprofit organization dedicated to education and social welfare. The collection consists of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, project and program files, fellowship recipient files, and financial records created and maintained by the organization. The records cover all aspects of the organization's activities from its inception in 1946 to shortly after its dissolution in 1983.
John Hay Whitney Foundation
Arrangement
The records are organized into two series: I. Administration, 1946-1994. II. Fellowship Recipient Files, 1950-1971.
Related Materials
John Hay Whitney and Betsey Cushing Whitney Family Papers (MS 1938) and the Greentree Stud & Stable Records (MS 1953).
Scope and Contents
The records document the organization and activities of the John Hay Whitney Foundation, a non-profit organization dedicated to education and social welfare. The collection consists of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, project and program files, fellowship recipient files, and financial records created and maintained by the organization. The records cover all aspects of the organization's activities from its inception in 1946 to shortly after its dissolution in 1983.
The collection provides a rich resource for the study of the Foundation. Material on the Foundation's origins and history are found in the collection, as is material related to the administration of the organization, such as bylaws, meeting minutes, and reports. The Trustees' and Members' minutes provide an accounting of decisions made in quarterly meetings, but very limited documentation about their deliberations. The records include members' minutes from December 1946 until September 1958 and April 1960 until September 1980 and trustees' minutes from December 1946 until May 1960 and June 1961 until June 1983. There is limited information regarding the Foundation's closing that can be found in correspondence and in financial records.
Financial records provide documentation on the financial state and transactions of the organization. Of particular interest are the files relating to the Internal Revenue Service's unsuccessful challenge to the Foundation's tax exempt status in 1971. The Foundation's response is thoroughly documented in the auditing files through legal records and correspondence. In addition to providing a full accounting of the organization's financial state, the Internal Revenue Service investigation response provides substantial background on the organization. On the whole, the financial files summarize the Foundation's financial history through incoming contributions and investments and outgoing grants and donations.
The collection's greatest strength is its documentation of the Foundation's projects and programs. The number and scope of projects and programs supported by the Foundation is well documented by the records. Of particular note are the files on the Foundation's fellowship programs: the Opportunity Fellowship Program and John Hay Fellows Program. The collection contains a substantial number of records pertaining to these two programs, including correspondence, photographs, and reports, as well as written commentary by fellows discussing their experiences in the programs between 1960 and 1963. Beyond the administrative files on the fellowships, the collection contains a complete run of Opportunity Fellowship and John Hay Fellows recipients' files, which provide information about the recipients. Material concerning the Foundation's smaller projects is limited to routine correspondence and brief descriptions of project goals and activity.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to the Yale community for research and teaching. Other researchers require the written permission of the Greentree Foundation to access the collection prior to January 1, 2050, after which the papers are open for research without restriction.
Biographical / Historical
The John Hay Whitney Foundation was originally named the Greenwood Foundation when it was founded by John Hay Whitney as a New York City-based, nonprofit corporation in 1946. Mr. Whitney returned from World War II with a social vision and desire to invest in people, ideas, and the future of post-war America. Greenwood Foundation's mission stemmed from Mr. Whitney's belief that education could help ethnic minorities and individuals from underprivileged backgrounds realize their potential. The Foundation supported talented individuals who had been excluded from mainstream American life because of race, gender, poverty or substandard schooling.
Between 1947 and 1949, the Foundation made grants for special projects led by other tax-exempt organizations in the fields of education, the humanities, and the social sciences. The first major grants were to the National Planning Association in Washington, D.C. for a labor relations study and a grant to support ten scholarships for African-American students studying the social sciences at Fisk University. In 1949, the Board of Trustees renamed the organization the John Hay Whitney Foundation and appointed subcommittees to administer their own programs stemming from the Foundation's mission.
In 1949, the John Hay Whitney Foundation started its earliest major initiative called the Opportunity Fellowship Program. From 1950 to 1971, the Opportunity Fellowship Program awarded 956 fellowships to individuals pursuing graduate or professional study in the humanities and the study of the arts. The Foundation's Committee of Award was appointed to review applications and select recipients, principally ethnic minorities and individuals from underprivileged backgrounds, who had encountered barriers to educational opportunities.
Two programs followed in 1951 which expanded the profile of a grant recipient to include professors. From 1951 to 1965, the Foundation established the Whitney-Fulbright Professorship to bring professors of the humanities and social sciences from other countries to teach at undergraduate colleges and universities in the United States. The Whitney Visiting Professors program named retired or retiring professors to a year of teaching at undergraduate colleges after completing work at their own institutions.
In 1952, the Foundation established their largest and most developed program, the John Hay Fellows Program. Designed to encourage education in the humanities through the training of secondary school teachers, there were two components: John Hay Year Fellows and John Hay Summer Fellows. The Humanities Committee awarded year-long fellowships to John Hay Year Fellows and coordinated planned study in the humanities at Yale University and Columbia University. In 1958, the Foundation secured additional financing from the Ford Foundation and the year-long program expanded to additional institutions, including Harvard University, Northwestern University, University of Chicago, and the University of California at Berkeley. This funding allowed for the creation of the John Hay Summer Fellows who attended Summer Institutes for the Humanities at Bennington College, Colorado College, and Williams College. Between 1952 and 1966, the program supported 688 John Hay Year Fellows and 1,359 John Hay Summer Fellows.
The 1970s marked a shift in the Foundation's focus from providing individual fellowships to supporting community-based educational and governmental agencies committed to the humanities and social sciences. After 1971, the Foundation supported one or two year projects related to, among other topics, farming, housing, education, and economic development in the United States.
John Hay Whitney served as the Foundation president from 1946 to 1970 and then chairman from 1970 until his death in 1982. Mr. Whitney planned for the dissolution of the Foundation in his estate and the Foundation ceased operations in 1983 but continued to spend down its funds on small grants and donations until 1986.
Source: John Hay Whitney Foundation, by Esther Raushenbush (Vol. I) and by Daniel Powell (Vol. II), 1972.
About the Creators was authored by Greentree Foundation.
Custodial History
Gift of the Greentree Foundation, 2009.
Charities; Endowments; High school teaching -- United States; Humanities -- United States; Minority college graduates; Minority students; Nonprofit organizations; Scholarships -- United States; John Hay Whitney Foundation
- Administration, 1946-1994; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged into five subseries: Administrative History, Boards and Committees, Correspondence, Financial, and Programs and Projects.
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents the administrative structure and activities of the John Hay Whitney Foundation. It includes general information about the foundation's organization, trustees' and members' minutes, financial records, and documentation about projects and programs that the John Hay Whitney Foundation supported from its inception in 1946 until its dissolution in 1983.
  The Administrative History subseries includes general information about the Foundation's organization and activities between 1946 and 1994. While the articles of incorporation and biennial reports provide summary information about the Foundation, items such as the background material for Ellis L. Phillips and the Foundation's 1970 conference transcript provide more detailed information about the Foundation's mission and activities.
  The Boards and Committees material includes quarterly meeting minutes and documentation about how the Foundation allocated grants to various projects and organizations. However, there is little material in this subseries on how funding decisions were made, simply a record of where Foundation money was awarded between 1946 and 1983. The Correspondence, though limited, provides documentation about decisions, programming, governance, and staff.
  The Financial records provide strong documentation of the Foundation's accounting, auditing, banking and financing activities from 1950 until 1986. Of particular interest are the auditing files which detail the Foundation's dealings with the Internal Revenue Service between 1970 and 1972 when the IRS challenged the Foundation's tax exempt status. In response, the Foundation and its legal team, led by Carter, Ledyard & Milburn, prepared a lengthy response that provides substantive insight into the Foundation's activities and vision for the future. The banking and financing records provide information about the Foundation's cash on hand, as well as documentation about the Foundation's investments between 1963 and 1982.
  The Programs and Projects supported by the Foundation are by far the best documented aspect of the organization. These materials document the projects and programs the Foundation funded between 1955 and 1983. Reports and recipient files provide rich documentation of the Opportunity Fellowship and John Hay Fellows programs (filed in Series II). After 1972, the Foundation focused on funding smaller, discrete projects around the United States. Each funded project has a file with basic information about the organization or individual's activities, the amount of money awarded, and minimal description of the project.
  - Administrative History
    - General, 1968-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - "Background material for Ellis L. Phillips, Jr.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Contains an overview of the John Hay Whitney Foundation's activities between 1949 and 1956.
    - Biennial reports, 1970, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bylaws, 1947, 1972, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Certificates
      - Incorporation and bylaws, correspondence regarding, 1946-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Existence of Foundation, State of New York, 1949-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Type of non-profit corporation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Conference (transcript), 1970 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Consists of a transcript of a conference held in New York City with the Foundation's Board of Trustees and senior advisors in attendance to discuss the Foundation's future direction.
    - Dissolution, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "John Hay Whitney Foundation Formal Report, 1956-1972" (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Policy and Procedures
      - General, 1952-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Publicity, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Power of Attorney, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Boards and Committees
    - Members, meeting minutes
      - 1946 December-1953 April (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 1954 May-1958 September (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1960 May-1967 September (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 1968 September-1974 December (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 1975 October-1980 September (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Trustees
      - Agendas, 1953-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Executive committee minutes, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Mailing list, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Minutes
        - 1946 December-1950 April (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - 1950 May-1951 September (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - 1951 October-1953 February (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - 1953 March-1954 March (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - 1954 April-1955 December (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - 1956 April-1960 May (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - 1961 June-1970 December (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - 1971 January-1974 December (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - 1975 March-1979 December (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - 1980 April-1983 June (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Chronological, 1954-1984 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Personnel, 1967-1983 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Trustees, 1970-1983 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Financial
    - Accounting
      - Appropriations and disbursements, 1971-1975 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Assets, liabilities, and fund balances, 1972-1978 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Budgets, 1967-1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Fees paid, 1969-1983 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
      - Ledger, 1962-1983 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Procedures, 1959-1982 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Auditing
      - Carter, Ledyard, & Milburn, 1969-1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence
        - Audit reports, 1950-1983 (Box 13, Folder 9)
        - Banks, 1951-1981 (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - Carter, Ledyard, & Milburn, 1950-1983 (Box 14, Folder 2)
        - Contributions and expenses, 1950-1981 (Box 14, Folder 3)
        - Members and trustees, 1950-1981 (Box 14, Folder 4)
        - Representation, 1950-1982 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Reports, 1961-1983 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Taxes
        - Automatic data processing, 1964-1968 (Box 14, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence and returns
          - 1946-1962 (Box 14, Folder 8-18)
          - 1962-1983 (Box 15, Folder 1-14)
          - 1987, 1982-1994 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
        - Grant Procedures (Internal Revenue Service codes), 1971-1984 (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Opportunity Fellows tax rulings, 1954-1970 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - New York city and state sales tax exemption, 1950-1971 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Tax exempt status investigation
          - Annual Report of Charitable Organizations, 1967-1986 (Box 17, Folder 2)
          - Carter, Ledyard & Milburn report, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
          - Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
          - Registration of charitable organization, State of New York, 1965-1986 (Box 18, Folder 4)
          - Revenue Agent review, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 5)
          - Taxes on taxable expenditures of private foundations (memoranda and reports), 1972-1982 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Banking
      - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company, 1957-1971 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - United States Trust Company
        - Custodian account, 1966-1986 (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
        - Investments, 1963-1982 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Securities, 1967-1970 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Financing
      - Contributions
        - General, 1974-1982, undated (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
        - Bequests, 1971-1986 (Box 19, Folder 8-9)
      - Refusals, 1951-1983 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Vibrontron Company Limited royalty payments, 1957-1971 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Projects and Programs
    - General, 1951-1978, 1984, undated (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - Allied credit union in northeastern North Carolina, 1979-1981 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Alternative schooling arrangement on Manhattan's West Side, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Banana Kelly Improvement Association, 1979-1982 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Blue Hills Homes Corporation (housing rehabilitation, Kansas City, Missouri), 1982-1983 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Boston Jobs Coalition, 1980-1982 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Brooklyn energy project, 1980-1982 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Buckeye Evaluation and Technical Institute, 1981-1982 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Cabrillo Tile Company, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Carr Square Village, Biddle Street Market (St. Louis, Missouri), 1982 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Central Pennsylvania village crafts, 1980-1981 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Christmas tree marketing at the Flathead Reservation, 1982-1983 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Cincinnati reinvestment project, 1981-1982 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Citizens Coal Company, 1980-1981 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Citizens Organized for Economic Development Incorporated (Denver, Colorado), 1982-1983 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Coal employment project in Tennessee, 1979-1980 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Coalition of Indian Controlled School Boards, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Commercial revitalization in Germantown, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1979-1981 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Community credit union in Santa Cruz County, 1978-1981 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Community thrift store of Mendenhall, Mississippi, 1979-1980 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Confederation Agricola de California, 1982 (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Connecticut Public Interest Research Group, 1981-1982 (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Debit insurance (Washington, District of Columbia), 1981-1982 (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Economic development of the Bishop Pavite Indian Reservation, 1980-1982 (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - "Economic and Political Change among the Gila River Paiute Indians", 1955 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - Examining city housing agencies in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1977-1978 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Exploratory Project for Economic Alternatives
      - Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Reports
        - "Capital and Community" (draft), 1976 (Box 21, Folder 3)
        - "Cooperatives at the Crossroads", 1977 (Box 21, Folder 4)
        - "A Positive Economic Future" (draft), 1976 (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
        - "A preliminary report on the feasibility of developing new approaches to altering long-term trends in the distribution of American income and wealth", 1972 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Exploring ways to improve education for a select member of New York City pupils, 1977-1978 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Farmers' home administration policies, 1977-1978 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Farmworker cooperative housing (Richgrove, California), 1980-1982 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Federation of community-controlled centers of Alabama (FOCAL, Incorporated), 1981-1983 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Greater Cleveland reinvestment project, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Hana district Pohaku non-profit corporation (agricultural cooperative), 1981-1982 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Harlem Parents School-Community Neighborhood Center, 1971, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Hartford Farmers' Market, 1979-1981 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Head Start, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Heart of Uptown Coalition, Incorporated (community development in Uptown, Chicago, Illinois), 1978-1982 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - High school education in New York City, improving, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - "Indian Adjustment and Indian Administration on the Uintah and Ouray Reservation", 1955 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Insurance anti-redlining and reinvestment in Chicago, 1981-1982 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - John Hay Fellows Program
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1953-1966, undated (Box 22, Folder 15)
        - Stocking, Fred, 1959-1962 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
          Includes correspondence between Stocking, a professor of rhetoric at Williams College and Charles Keller, director of the John Hay Fellows program, about humanities lectures, students, and routine business.
      - Danforth Foundation, 1966, circa 1969 (Box 23, Folder 3)
        Includes correspondence and a grant proposal to the Danforth Foundation.
      - Ford Foundation, 1956-1960, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
        Includes correspondence between the Ford Foundation and the John Hay Whitney Foundation, grant proposals to the Ford Foundation, and grant awards from the Ford Foundation outlining their support of the John Hay Fellows program's expansion in 1958 and in 1960.
      - "Humanistic Studies at the High School" (discussion meeting reports), 1955, 1957-1959 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Newsletter, 1955-1956 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Participants
        - Comments from, 1956-1962 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
        - Lists of, 1952-1965 (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - "The Schools We Came From", 1962, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 2)
          Includes written testimonials from John Hay Fellows about the schools they taught in before joining the program.
        - Stipends, 1963-1964 (Box 25, Folder 3)
      - Photographs
        - General, 1961, 1964-1966, undated (Box 25, Folder 4-7)
        - Columbia University program, Undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
        - Joint meeting, Columbia University, 1956-1958 (Box 25, Folder 9)
        - National Education Association, 1958 (Box 25, Folder 10)
      - Publicity
        - Clippings, 1955-1964, undated (Box 25, Folder 11)
        - Fliers, 1953-1965, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Press releases
          - General, 1952-1958, 1963 (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
          - Fellowship announcements
            - 1958 (Box 26, Folder 4)
            - 1962 (Box 26, Folder 5)
            - 1963 (Box 26, Folder 6)
            - 1965 (Box 26, Folder 7)
          - Winners announcements
            - 1959, 1961 (Box 26, Folder 8-10)
            - 1962-1964 (Box 27, Folder 1-7)
            - 1965 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
      - Reports
        - General, 1955, undated (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - Annual (fiscal year)
          - 1958-1959 (Box 28, Folder 4)
          - 1959-1960 (Box 28, Folder 5)
          - 1960-1961 (Box 28, Folder 6)
          - 1961-1962 (Box 28, Folder 7)
          - 1962-1963 (Box 29, Folder 1)
          - 1963-1964 (Box 29, Folder 2)
          - 1964-1965 (Box 29, Folder 3)
          - 1965-1966 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Campuses, 1952-1958, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 5)
        - Dean of Faculty of Arts and Sciences, Harvard University, 1962-1963 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Evaluation, 1952, 1954, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
        - Expansion, Undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
        - Humanities committee, 1955 (Box 30, Folder 1)
        - "The Outlook for the Humanities in the Public High School", Undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
        - Progress, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Seminar minutes, 1952-1953, undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
      - "Seminar on the Humanities", 1951 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - Summer Institute for the Humanities
        - Participants
          - Comments from, 1960-1961 (Box 30, Folder 6-8)
          - List of, 1964-1965 (Box 31, Folder 1)
          - Stipends, 1964 (Box 31, Folder 2)
        - Photographs
          - Bennington College, 1961-1963, 1965 (Box 31, Folder 3)
          - Colorado College, 1961 (Box 31, Folder 4)
            - Oversize (Box 34, Folder 1)
          - Williams College, 1959, 1961-1963 (Box 31, Folder 5-6)
        - Publicity materials, 1959-1964 (Box 31, Folder 7)